<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The curse of sacriledge Preached in a priuate parish church, the Sunday before Michaelmas last. To which are annexed some certaine quære's, which are pertinent to the vnmasking of our homebred church-robbers. D.E.B.</title>
            <author>Brouncker, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00200</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1025</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851069</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851069</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00200)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 869:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The curse of sacriledge Preached in a priuate parish church, the Sunday before Michaelmas last. To which are annexed some certaine quære's, which are pertinent to the vnmasking of our homebred church-robbers. D.E.B.</title>
                  <author>Brouncker, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 38, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield, printer to that famous Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>D.E.B. = Doctor Edward Brouncker.</note>
                  <note>"A catalogue of such quæres as are submitted by the author in all due respect to the iudgment of the wisest sonnes of his mother the church" has caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16324:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> CVRSE OF SACRILEDGE. PREACHED IN A PRIVATE PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church, the Sunday before Michaelmas laſt. <hi>TO WHICH ARE ANNEXED ſome certaine Quaere's, which are pertinent to the vnmasking of our homebred Church-Robbers.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ACTS 4. 20. &amp; 21.</bibl>
               <p>Whether it be right, in the ſight of God, to harken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you more then vnto God, iudge yee; for we cannot but ſpeake the things which we haue ſeene and heard.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>D. E. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT OXFORD, <hi>Printed by</hi> IOHN LICHFIELD, <hi>Printer to that famous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16324:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16324:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> CALL heaven to witneſse, the prime marke I ayme at by this my declamation againſt Sacriledge, is the flouriſhing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of this Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and that by diverſion of thoſe Iudgments which by the perſpectiue of the word, I deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry approaching towards vs, vnleſse a <hi>non plus vltra</hi> bee ſet to this ſtill ſpreading Leaproſie. Meruaile not how I dare <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> thus freely ſpeake in a poynt that tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſo farre on the <hi>vtile</hi> and <hi>iucundum</hi> of thouſands, and ſome of thoſe too <hi>Grandies,</hi> For I am confident hee is no Legitimate Prieſt, who is afraid to thwart any ſinne, though neuer ſo much backt and vpheld by an arme of fleſh; If ſinners haue browes of braſse, Gods Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors muſt not haue hearts captiuated with feare &amp; baſhfullnes. If the Laities hands be fraudulently buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſnatching and filching, our tongues muſt not bee lockt vp from ſharp and zealous reprouing. It is the Character of a wiſe man to bee free in Rebukes, when vice is bold and daring. For myne owne part I deſire no longer to liue then I dare reſolutly ſay with <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the great, <hi>In cauſa in qua Deo placere cupio, homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes non formido,</hi> As I acknowledge myne owne ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, ſo withall I remember that one of the <hi>Infantery</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16324:3"/> may doe acceptable ſeruice in the field, as well as one of the <hi>Cauagliery.</hi> An ordinary Purſiua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deliuer the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of a King, as well as a Herald at Armes; That a musket may ſet a Cannon a roaring. That their paines was as requiſite for the Temple who brought but stones and Cement, as theirs Who brought Gold and rich orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments It is the Lords method to bring great things to paſse by ſmall beginnings, to ordaine ſtrength out of the mouthes of babes and ſucklings. And if like little deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Dauid</hi> I ſhall not conquer this vast <hi>Goliah,</hi> yet if I ſhall put the worthies of <hi>Iſraell</hi> into Armes who are likely to winne the day, I ſhall deeme my ſelfe ſo happy, as to cry out with him, <hi>ite triumphales circum mea tempora lauri.</hi> Nor mayeſt thou deeme this ouermuch preſumption, when as victory is neuer wholly aſcribed to him who strikes the laſt ſtroke, but they who gaue the first or ſecond onſet, may clayme a leafe or two in the triumphant Laurell, And all bee it I ſubſcribe to him who ſayes hee ſees no reaſon that ſoe high a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as Diuinity ſhould bee preſented to the people in the ſordid ragges of the tongue; Nor that hee who ſpeakes from the father of languages ſhould deliuer his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in an ill one, Yet haue I in this my Sermon followed both the counſaile of bleſſed <hi>Auſtine</hi> when hee ſayes, <note place="margin">Lib. 4. de do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti cap. 10.</note> 
               <hi>qui docet, vitabit omnia verba quae non docent,</hi> Hee who teacheth must bauke all thoſe words which teach not. His reaſon is, <hi>quid enim prodeſt locutionis inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritas, quam non ſequitur intellectus audientis.</hi> As alſo that of learned <hi>Toſtatus, tenetur Doctor illo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do docere, quo ſentiat diſcipulis vtile eſſe,</hi> A Teacher muſt vſe that method by which hee may moſt profit
<pb facs="tcp:16324:3"/> thoſe who are learners And that becauſe (ſaith hee) <hi>docere non eſt propter docentem, ſed propter eos qui</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Comment: in 3. prolog. Hieron: Qu. 17. tom. 1 in Mattheum.</note> 
               <hi>docentur.</hi> Teaching hath for its obiect the hearers and not the ſpeaker himſelfe. If thou aske mee why I craue not the protection of ſome powerfull <hi>Moecenas,</hi> know first, that as it is held a folly to haue recourſe by our praiers to the Saincts in heauen when the way lyes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to Christ himſelfe, ſo I take it to bee needleſse to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for mans countenancing of that which I am well aſſured the Allmighty God accepts of as a ſweet-ſmelling Sacrifice offered vp from the Altar of a wel-diſpoſed heart. As alſo I am of opinion, I may, as fitly as euer <hi>Diogenes,</hi> light a Candle at noone day, and goe vp and downe with a <hi>hominem quaero</hi> as being ignorant where to meet with a man, which ſome way or other falls not vnder the curſe of my text, who either by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying impropriated tithes, or by pleading vniuſt Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes, makes not a ſheepe of this or that ſhepheard by withdrawing from him part of his annuall accrewing fleece. Now for a farewell, let mee entreat thee to weigh and examine theſe enſuing lines without preiudice, ſo ſhall I hope at length to reap ſome part of the large crop of my deſire.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the rough and craggy way to bliſſe E. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16324:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16324:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>MALACHIE 3. 9.</bibl>
               <q>Yee are curſed with a curſe, for yee haue robbed me even this whole Nation.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter we meete with an Aſſize held, wherein God is the Iudge, the parties arraigned are the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin,</hi> the offence Sacriledge or theft of holy things, the witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes both their owne conſciences though ſtrumpet like, they denie it with their tongues, as alſo the too too viſible neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the Lords ſervice in the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites,</hi> and that through want of maintenance, and laſtly the ſentence of condemnation which lies in the words of the text, <hi>Yee are curſed with a curſe.</hi> In which ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence you may fitly take notice of theſe diſtinct parts;</p>
            <p>Firſt of a <hi>Curſe</hi> inflicted, <hi>maledicendo maledicti, yee are curſed with a curſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly of the parties on whome the <hi>curſe</hi> lights, and theſe lie in the <hi>vos, Yee,</hi> and theſe yee, are the tribe of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:16324:5"/>
            <p> Thirdly of the reaſon of this <hi>curſe, quia ſpoliaſtis me, for yee haue robbed me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly of the vniverſality of this ſinne, <hi>gens omnis ipſa, even the whole Nation,</hi> of each of which, in its order, as God ſhall enable and the time permit.</p>
            <p>Before we can well knowe the <hi>quid,</hi> what it is to be <hi>curſed,</hi> wee muſt firſt find out the <hi>quis,</hi> who it is that <hi>curſeth.</hi> Now both God and man are ſaid to <hi>curſe,</hi> Man <hi>curſes</hi> when hee prayes or wiſhes for any ill to befall him with whom hee is offended, whoſe <hi>curſes</hi> haue no neceſſitating power of cauſing and induceing the evill which he wiſhes and prayes for, but may fall out to bee but as Arrowes ſhote againſt a ſtone wall which ſends them back vpon him that ſhott them. As for God, hee <hi>curſes</hi> other wiſe, his <hi>curſe</hi> is an actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all inflicting of ſome ſmarting punniſhment the force of which none can reſiſt, it hitts and miſſes not, as ſoone as it is decreed, As Gods <hi>benedicere</hi> his bleſſing of a man is no verball thing, no contingent future act, but a preſent conferring of ſome good; So this <hi>male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicere,</hi> his <hi>curſing,</hi> is not a bare ſpeaking ill of a man, though it ſounds no more in grammer, but it is a true reall inflicting of ſomthing ill to fleſh and bloud; So that here when the Prophet tells <hi>Iudath</hi> they are <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> wee are to vnderſtand ſome preſent calamity laid on them by the Lord, Namely, that of pale-cheeked and cleane-teetht famine, for ſo the vulgar renders the originall, <hi>in penuriâ maledicti eſtis,</hi> yee are curſed with penury and want, The reaſon of which tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is becauſe as bleſſing imports multiplication and encreaſe, ſo malidiction implyes diminution and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16324:5"/> to which as a further Commentary, may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that curſe which God laid on Cain, <hi>maledictus es a terrâ,</hi> thou art curſed from the earth, even by fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a want of that fruite, which otherwiſe the earth would have yeelded thee; Where, by the way, you may take notice of this Concluſion, A want of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, eſpecially thoſe prime neceſſaries, food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a heauy curſe. But I paſſe this, and come to the examining of the reaſon why God tells the men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> they are curſed, A man would thinke the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent want vnder which the groned, was ſufficient to make them apprehenſiue of a Curſe; why then doth God in direct words tell them they are curſed?</p>
            <p>Two reaſons may bee rendred of it,</p>
            <p>One is that thereby they might bee put in minde that he had a hand in their miſery, that it came not by vncertaine chance and peradventure, but by his ſetled determinate will and pleaſure, that it came ſo from him, as without him they had ſtill ſwomme in a full ſea of plenty, without feeling the leaſt ebbe of ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city:</p>
            <p>The other, and it is the chiefeſt, is, that they beeing infallibly aſſured they were puniſhed by him for their Sacriledge, they might be ſtirred vp ſo to hate that ſinne, as to abandon it for the time to come, yea ſo to deteſt it as to deale by every the leaſt thought of committing it hereafter, what God commanded to bee done to the Children of the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> even to deſtroy all not to ſpeare an infant, the leaſt tempting thought vnto it. <hi>O altitudinem miſericordiarum Dei,</hi> O the fathomleſſe depth of the mercies of God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16324:6"/> to ſinnfull man! what Rhetorique doth hee vſe to call him backe from ſinning, that ſo he may ceaſe from ſmiting? what inexpreſſable art doth hee ſhow to make him ſenſible of the danger hee is in, how hee is environed with troopes of curſes, Curſes for his bodie curſes for his eſtate, and curſes (which is worſt of all) for his ſoule, and thoſe too, not to bee ſhunned or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, by any other meanes (which can poſſibly fall, within the ſphere of his actiuitie) but only by a heart breaking and renting amendment.</p>
            <p>Why then are wee the Ambaſſedors of <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> men ſent for the ſalvation of your ſoules, if you will practically heare and receiue our arrands, why (I ſay) are we blamed, why thought hardlie of, yea blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, as if wee ſpeake from private ſpirits, when wee tell you, that as your ſinnes bee the ſame with <hi>Iudahs,</hi> ſo your puniſhments in all likelihood will bee the ſame, That as you ſtik not to robb God an his Prieſts with them, and that with a like impudent browe of deniall, ſo you are already, &amp; will hereafter more bee curſed, if you continue that your theft; For ſhame make not good that proverbe <hi>Plaine dealing is a Iewell, but hee that vſeth it ſhall die a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi> I have often dealt plainly with you in many things which are amiſſe amongſt you. but chiefly in that wherein you are growne old and rooted, I meane your theft by pleading vniuſt cuſtomes in ſatiſfaction of tithes; O doe not (I beſeech you) make mee to die a begger, by gaining few or none of your ſoules, to the embraceing and kiſſing of theſe faire Ladies Truth and Equitie I ſaie Begger, For truly the winning of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16324:6"/> your hearts from that bewitching <hi>Siren</hi> of <hi>Sacriledge</hi> is the riches I moſt deſire, full baggs and lardge yard lands ſhall not ſo much glad mee, as your growth in grace; Vntill the time then I ſhall gather from you, (who are now allmoſt dead trees, the livelie ſweete fruits of amendment: bee not diſpleaſed at my lopping &amp; pruning of you by ſharpe and keene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes, as long as your mouthes are accuſtomed to plead for cuſtomes, and your hearts ſecretlie to ſay, O bleſſed Cuſtomes becauſe fillers of our purſes, ſo long expect: I follow the never-erring ſtepps of my Maker in proclaiming Iudgments againſt you for ſo doing, ſaying vnto you in the words of my text, <hi>yee are curſed with a curſe,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Even yee;</hi> which is my ſecond circumſtance. yee; who are a choſen generation, a Roiall Prieſthood, a peculiar people, from whence this obſervation will naturallie ariſe.</p>
            <p>No outward temporall favour or prerogative can priviledge or protect a Sinner from the puniſhing hand of God. you ſee the <hi>(yee)</hi> in the Text lye open to a curſe, though they were of the noble ſtock of <hi>Abraham,</hi> though Lords of a land flowed with milk and honie, a land which was as the diamond in the ring, as the Apple in the eye, and as the heart in the bodie of the world, A land ſo full of goodly men, as if the clouds had ſhowred them downe; It is a true ſaying, <hi>Noxa caput ſequitur,</hi> puniſhments are to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners what ſhaddowes are to bodies, As there is no bodie without it's ſhadowe, ſo is there no vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſinner without ſome puniſhment or other wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16324:7"/> on him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Carthaginians hate to Rome</hi> was not ſo ſurelie entailed on their Children, as whipps are on tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors;</p>
            <p>Theſe are twynnes, on following the other at the heeles, yea two maine linkes in the ſure chaine of Gods providence; The Poet could ſay,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Rarò antecedentem ſcelestum</l>
               <l>Deſervit pede paena claudo:</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which I Engliſh in theſe words of God to Cain in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> if thou doeſt not well, ſinne lieth at the dore; whereby ſinne is by the figure <hi>Metalep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin,</hi> meant the puniſhment of ſinne, <hi>Vbi peccatum ibi procella</hi> where ſin is, there will be a puniſhing ſtorme, a Sea of Iniquitie will ſurelie drawe after it a hell of torments; Vengance is a doge, which lies ever readie when leaue ſhalbee given him, to take a Sinner by the throate, and though this dog bee for a time muſled and layed aſleepe, through Gods long ſuffering pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence yet ſhall this <hi>Cerberus</hi> at length bee let looſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on willfull ſinners; Puniſhments are as bailiffs, or as Seriants, ever readie at Gods commaund to ſeaze on his Debters, Sinners; And though ſome bad Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers doe for many yeares together, through the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long conniving mercie of God, eſcape their Arreſts, yet queſtionles they will at length lay hands on them, yea at laſt there ſhall bee no place of ſanctuarie, no priviledge or protection to bee obtained, Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengfull hand will not be kept out of a caſtle of braſſe, the ſea is not ſo deepe but vengeance can fathome it, nor the world ſo wide but Iudgment can quickly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16324:7"/> and compaſſe it. <hi>Quod differtur non aufertur,</hi> Delayes are not exemptions, a Reprivall and a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don are two things, Gods mercifull expectation is not a perpetuall protection; Though God created the Angels with ſo great care and loue, as to make them allmoſt Gods, by the manifold perfections they were endued withall, yet when they ſinned againſt him, there was nothing could ſaue them from the heavie ſtroke of his wrath: Though God crowned had <hi>Adam</hi> with manie rare bleſſings, as namelie,</p>
            <p>Firſt with a happie place of abode, <hi>Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly with a ſweete Companion and readie helper <hi>Eue;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdlie with princelie power and authoritie over all other Creatures, yet loe when hee neglects his Makers Command, nothing is of force to protect him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the curſe of a <hi>mortem morieris,</hi> thou ſhalt die the death, what did ever either beautie, witt, or policy, or large and full barnes, or the loud wide applauſe of the people, ſaue a <hi>Sinner</hi> from the wihp of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Iuſtice; The vnnaturally ambitious <hi>Abſolon</hi> the treacherouſſe politique <hi>Achitophel,</hi> the vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perplexed rich man, togeather with the vaineglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſelfe Deifying <hi>Herod</hi> the king, can and will tell you, Nay; Tremble then, O thou man whoſoever thou art, though a darling of fortune, if thy conſcience once tels thee thou haſt any ſinne lying hid in thy heart, as that Babiloniſh garment and wedg of gold did in <hi>Achans</hi> tent, tremble I ſay, for feare of ſome judgment which may ſpeedily ſeaze on thee for it. Knowe there is a hand-writing gone out againſt thee,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16324:8"/> as there was againſt <hi>Baltaſar,</hi> to blott out which, thou haſt no other way or meanes: then to ſhed the bitter ſharp teares of a repentant heart; Theſe indeed, though thy judgment were written in ſteele or braſſe, may eate and weare it out. Knowe thou haſt ſeverall curſes following, and dogging thee at the heeles, from which thou can'ſt not bee delivered but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering thy ſelfe from thy ſinne, renounce that, and all curſes ſhall forſake thee. As when the bodie dies, the ſhadow vaniſhes ſo when the cauſe is removed, the effect ceaſes. what did not <hi>Iſraells</hi> ſinne take from her thoſe titles of high honor, <hi>Ammi</hi> and <hi>Ruhama,</hi> my people, and the obiect of mercie, and left her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed thereof, onlie thoſe of diſgrace <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>horror, Loammi</hi> and <hi>Loruhama,</hi> not my people, and not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of a looke of mercie; Did not ſinne chriſton her a new, as it were by theſe names of miſerie <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>forſaken</hi> and <hi>deſolate,</hi> who formerlie was called <hi>Hephzebah</hi> Gods delight, and <hi>Beulah</hi> his wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded land, <hi>Eſay</hi> the 62. verſ. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> yea might ſhee not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe haue ſtill bene a Crowne of glorie in the hand of the Lord, and a roiall diademe in the hand of her God, as it is in the former verſe of that Chapter.</p>
            <p>Did not ſinne (notwithſtanding all her priuiledges and prerogatives,) twice carrie <hi>Iudah</hi> into Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, twice deſtroie her temples; ſhall wee then (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) looke to eſcape the like fatall Iudgments, if wee runne on ſtill in a reſolution of living as wee liſt, of putting the Almighties mercie as it were on the tenter hookes; Surelie it will at length breake forth into furie, The date of it will ere long bee expired,</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16324:8"/>
            <p> Iuſtice will another while rule &amp; ſway the Scepter, if wee will not with <hi>Nineveh</hi> repent whileſt our 40 daies laſt, then ſhall wee feele the truth of what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie a <hi>Ionas</hi> haue preached vnto vs, even a floud of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes falling on our heads, and that which is worſt of all, wee may feele them when leaſt wee dreame of them; So was the caſe of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> ſo of <hi>Dathan, Corah,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> ſo of <hi>Lots wife,</hi> ſo of <hi>Herod,</hi> of <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Zaphirah,</hi> ſo of <hi>Zimri,</hi> and of <hi>Coſbi,</hi> and ſo likewiſe of a thouſand others; And what likelihood is there, ours ſhall not likewiſe ſo be? what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever befalls one, may befall all, Iudgments may bee fruitfull as well as ſinnes; For concluſion of the point, I can ſay but this, Let one ſodainneſſe beget another, the ſodainneſſe of Gods Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts worke in each of vs ſodaine and ſpeedie determination of amending his owne waies, of hearkening to the checks and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troules of his owne Conſcience, by which courſe wee ſhall avoid the like accuſation, which here is laide to <hi>Iudahs</hi> charge, namelie of beeing <hi>Robbers</hi> which is my third generall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yee have robbed mee:</hi> So reads our laſt Engliſh tranſlation, which comes nearer to the originall then either the vulgars <hi>Configitis</hi> yee crucifie or faſten, or the <hi>Septuagints ſupplantatis</hi> yee ſupplant, or <hi>Suma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus his defraudatis</hi> yee defraude, or our former En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh tranſlation, yee ſpoile, Though each of thoſe may well ſtand and bring a man with in compaſſe of robberie; from which accuſation there is offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your thoughts this plaine note or concluſion.</p>
            <p>In Gods account hee is a <hi>theefe</hi> and a <hi>Robber,</hi> who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16324:9"/> any wayes withholds Tithes or offerings from the <hi>Prieſt</hi> the right owner; I ſay any way, becauſe hee not onlie offends againſt the eight Commandement thou ſhalt not ſteale, who violentlie takes from a man, either the whole or any part of his goods, as high-way theeues and open oppreſſors vſe to doe, but hee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe who by any cloſe vnder hand dealing or cunning taking of advantage poſſeſſes himſelfe of what bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to another, yea though it bee but in thought wiſh or deſire, <hi>At quid ad nos?</hi> But what's this to vs, you'le aske? yea you'le ſay, though it cannot bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that the non paiment of Tithes Firſt-fruits, and other offerings, was theft <hi>in graine</hi> amongſt the <hi>Iewes</hi> and that by vertue either of their <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> or <hi>Iudiciall Law,</hi> yet followes it not the caſe ſhould bee the ſame with vs, who are onlie bound to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Morall lawe; As for the ceremoniall and iudiciall they now tye no farther then Civill humane authoritie, reviues and ratifies them, For Anſwere, It is confeſſed, it hath heretoſore and ſtill is queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſome, whether the paiements of tithes fall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the morall Law, though I muſt tell you, that ſome hath bin made vp partly by ſuch as have ſtudied more the defence of the <hi>Popes</hi> vniuſt actions, then truthes oracles, and partlie by others, who out of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or malice, or both togeather, have taken e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie thing almoſt which is related, either in the booke of <hi>Exodus</hi> or <hi>Leviticus,</hi> to belong onlie to the ceremoniall or iudiciall lawes; But however, I ſhall (God willing) make it appeare vnto you, and that by away, which as yet was never queſtioned by any of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16324:9"/> the learned, That thoſe lay-men are grand theeues, who at any time with hold or take vnto themſelves, <hi>Decimam Sacram,</hi> tithes once giuen for maintenance of any holie or Religious worke, which that I may the more fullie make good vnto you, Let mee lay downe two Theoremes or propoſitions, the one this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tithes are in the number of thoſe things which are ſacred;</hi> By tithes I vnderſtand the tenth part of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever encreaſe comes to a man in his temporall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and by <hi>Sacred</hi> is meant ſuch things as are devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, dedicated, given, and conſecrated to the worſhip and ſervice of the Lord, the conſecration beeing a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying of them, when before they were of prophane, civill, and ordinarie vſe; Thus both <hi>Gramarians,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Divines.</hi> The other propoſition this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whatſoever is once dedicated and freelie beſtowed to a holie vſe, can never, with out the guilt of ſinne, bee taken a way or imployed to any other vſe then what is holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prove the firſt, I ſhall offer vnto you foure rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</p>
            <p>The firſt is taken from the parties to whome tithes from the infant cradle-age of the world have ſtill bnee payd, namelie to men conſecrated and ſet apart from others, I ſay cradle-age of the world, For albeit wee heare of ſome though not of a ſacred function who haue enjoyed tithes, yet you are to knowe that Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the beſt Interpreters of the actions of fore-paſt times tell vs, they poſſeſſed, but either as wages from houſes of Religion, for ſome care and paines taken in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16324:10"/> ſecuring vnto them theire peace and ſaftie, or as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices from affrighted and perplexed men, who fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ſhould not bee able to defend their right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt tirannicall Princes and other great ones ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed vnto them part of their eſtates, which was alſo <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sayi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Cap.</hi> 12. <hi>n.</hi> 4.</note> the verie caſe of the Abbies and Monaſteries here in England, at the diſſolution, the Poſſeſſors of which places were enforced to reſigne vp all their right ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and intereſt in them into the Kings hands: for feare they ſhould otherwiſe haue loſt all, even their future liuelyhood. A ſecond is drawne from the name which is given to the tithes which Lay men poſſeſſe, they are called <hi>Impropriations,</hi> ſignifying thereby, they are improperlie placed, that they are to ſpeake in the phraſe of old, <hi>tanquam piſsis in arido, vel monachus in oppido,</hi> As much out of their place, as a fiſh is on dry land, or a monke in a faire or market, yea I may add, as a Crowne would bee richer on a <hi>Iack Cades,</hi> or a <hi>Wat Tilers</hi> head, naie more, as a <hi>Saint</hi> would bee in <hi>Hell,</hi> or a <hi>Divell</hi> in <hi>Heaven;</hi> A third reaſon is fetcht from that Act of the 32. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. which was made <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 7.</note> to enable laymen to ſue for tithes, when as before, (ſaith the preface to that ſtatute) they could haue no proceedings either in the Eccleſiaſticall or Common Law for the recoverie of them from thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to pay them; Whereby it evidentlie appeares, the State (till then) tooke laymen to bee no fit poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of ſuch conſecrated endowments, yea doth not laymen's ſuing for them at this day in ſpirituall Courts, publiſh to the vnderſtanding of anie ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man, that tithes are a Spirituall Income and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16324:10"/> to none but ſuch as are of a ſpirituall function. The fourth an laſt lies in that welknowne rule or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi> in the third Chapter of his booke <hi>contra haerices</hi> We are greatlie to take care, ſaith hee, wee hold that for a truth which in all places at all times, and by all perſons hath beene received and entertained, which is all one allmoſt with that of <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> orator, <hi>in omnire conſenſio omnium gentium lex naturae putanda est &amp; inſtar mille demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrationum talis conſenſio apud bonos eſse debet;</hi> The Conſent of all nations about any one thing is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken (ſaith hee) for the law of nature, and to bee of more authoritie with the good and vertuous, then a thouſand demonſtrations. Now to bring home theſe rules to the Buſines in hand, Let me aſke, was there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Nation, if once it had but the outward face of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which hath not conſecrated her tithes to ſome God Did not <hi>Abraham</hi> long before the lawe was given dedicate his tithes to the true God in <hi>Malchiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> the Prieſt? Did not likewiſe <hi>Iacob</hi> ſtronglie bind himſelfe to the performance of the ſame dutie by a ſollemne vowe? Did not our forefathers in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome manie hundreds of yeares ſince, freelie reſigne them vp to the propagation of Gods worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; And read wee not of tithes vowed to <hi>Hercules,</hi> to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> to <hi>Apollo</hi> and to ſeverall other of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Deities? The learned Antiquarie M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Seldon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth thus much; May I not, yea muſt I not, then drawe this concluſion out of ſuch premiſſes, <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> tithes haue in all ages been in the Inventory of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated goods, and accounted of as a ſacred tribute
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16324:11"/> to the King of heaven, And ſo I haſten to my ſecond theorem or propoſition; Namelie this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whatſoever is once dedicated, and freely beſtowed to a holy vſe, can never without the guilt of ſinne, bee taken away and imployed to any vſe which is not holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth of which is proved by three arguments, the firſt ſtands in ſome texts of Scripture, the ſecond in the deffinition of Sacriledge, And the third in the opinion of thoſe verie men who haue declared them ſelues againſt the <hi>ius divinum</hi> the divine right of tithes.</p>
            <p>The Texts bee chieflie ſixe, Foure in the old teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and two in the new; The firſt is that of <hi>Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> the laſt, where there is an expreſſe Act of heavens Parliament, <hi>That whatſoever is once devoted or made holy by guift vnto the Lord, cannot bee recalled or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, but vpon termes of diſadvantage to him who recalles it.</hi> The ſecond, that of <hi>Geneſis</hi> the 47. where wee reade how <hi>Ioſeph</hi> would not meddle with the gleabes of the <hi>Egyptian Prieſts,</hi> and that for no other reaſon but becauſe they were conſecrated lands, the propertie of which was not to bee changed, The third is that of <hi>Proverbs</hi> the 20. and 25. where the holie Ghoſt tells vs plainelie, <hi>It is a ſnare to the man, Who devoureth that which is holy.</hi> The fourth, that of <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> the 5. where wee read, God diſlikes of <hi>Baltaſars</hi> drinking in the ſacred veſſells of the temple, written in the capitall red Letters of his diſtruction. The fifth is that of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 2. where wee meete with our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> whipping and ſcourging men out of the Temple, his fathers houſe, and that for no other reaſon, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16324:11"/> ſometimes they fold ſuch cattell &amp; doues there, as were of vſe for ſacrifice; which our <hi>Saviours</hi> zeale in behalfe of that conſecrated place ſtops the months of all thoſe who ſhall ſay that that Decree in the laſt of <hi>Leviticus</hi> was but ceremoniall, for though ſo much bee granted, yet cannot hee bee excuſed, who in thoſe dayes of the goſpell ſhall convert to a common and prophane vſe, either a holy place or a holy revenue, And that for as much as it is a rule approved of by the ſuffrage of the beſt Divines, that whatſoever branch either of the ceremoniall or iudiciall law wee finde put in practice by our <hi>Saviour</hi> or his Apoſtles, even that ſtraight way became morall and ties for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. The laſt text is that of Acts the 5. where <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Zaphira</hi> his wife are both ſtricken with ſodaine and vnexpected death, for committing ſacriledge though in the leaſt degree, I ſay leaſt degree, becauſe they did but with draw vnder hand part of that mony which in ſhowe they had formerlie devoted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to a pious and religious vſe, even the reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtles from the arreſt of beggerie, And ſo much for the firſt argument to proue, that whatſoever is once conſecrated to any religious vſe, cannot quite bee taken away from that or the like vſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond lies in the deffinition of Sacriledge, which is this <hi>Sacrilegium est rei ſacrae violatio,</hi> It is an a buſing and perverting of the right vſe of holy things: ſo <hi>Aquinas,</hi> where by holie things hee vnderſtands <note place="margin">22 <hi>Q. Act.</hi>
               </note> any thing which is ſet apart to a holie vſe, and by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, hee meanes the imploiment of ſuch things to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16324:12"/> civill common and prophane vſe. whence alſo that derivation. <hi>Sacrilegium quaſi ſacrilaedium;</hi> ſo called becauſe it prophanes holy things, To which let mee add that full deſcription made of it by that Proteſtant Schooleman <hi>Hieronymus Zanchius,</hi> It is in his firſt booke <hi>de externo cultu</hi> and 17. Chapter, hee commits ſacriledge (ſaith hee) who any way gets into his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion holie things ſuch as haue been conſecrated and given to any religious and holie vſe whatſoever, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther find I anie other diffinition, deſcription, or Eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologie which in effect is not the ſame; It followes therefore of neceſſitie, that Hee is a theefe who med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles with holie things, beeing no conſecrated perſon;</p>
            <p>Now my third and laſt argument ſtands in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thoſe men, who though enimies to the <hi>ius morale divinum,</hi> the divine morall right of tithes, yet allow they not any converting of things conſecrated to ordinary and prophane vſe. In the firſt place I ſhall produce him, whoſe memorie I knowe is to all thoſe who are <hi>Canaanites</hi> to the Church, like the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the perfume that is made by the art of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary, I meane M. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> who in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary on thoſe words of the Proverbs the 20. and 25. <hi>(It is a ſnare to the man who devoureth that which is holy)</hi> will tell you at large: Firſt how that may be called holy which either by Gods appointment, or by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tary gift, is addicted &amp; devoted to holy vſes: 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, that by holy vſes is meant whatſoever is beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards the maintenance either of the Miniſters of the Goſpell, or of Schooles, or Hoſpitalls: 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, that however tithes and offerings be not now due by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16324:12"/> of Gods immediate conſtitution, yet are they due by vertue of humane conſtitutions, and guifts of men, yea ſo due, as that hee makes himſelfe a Robber of God, who withdrawes them from thoſe vſes for which they were given. Laſtly hee'le there ſhew you, that the transferring and converting of conſecrated things to a mans private ordinary vſe, is like that booke in the 10. of the Revelation, which was ſweete in the mouth but bitter in the belly, for though Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge be ſweete and pleaſant in the mouth, that is at the beginning, yet will it be bitter in the belly, that is at the latter end, as alſo, that it falls out to ſuch carnall men, as it doth to fiſh and birds, who with one bitt of the deſired baite, looſe their liues, yea with <hi>Eſau</hi> they forfeite their birth-right heaven for a trifle, a meſſe as it were of pottage. In a ſecond place I might ſend you to one who is likewiſe neare you both in affection and place of abode, but I hold it needleſſe ſeeing he is but the formers Eccho, turn'd into Engliſh. In a third let <note place="margin">M. Cleaver.</note> him ſpeake, whome the tithe Cormorants of this land hoped ſhould haue proued ere this, ſuch an one, as of whome they might haue trivmphantly ſaid: Behold the man who is ſet vp for the throwing downe of a rich and learned Church, that a beggerly ignorant pentionary one, may come in the ſteed of it. It is M. <hi>Seldon</hi> who ſo farr fruſtrates their expectation, as in the ſixt Chapter of his Reviewe to ſay, It is a groſſe error to thinke that therefore tithes may now be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by lay-men with a good conſcience, becauſe it is queſtioned whether the Miniſter can demand them <hi>iure divino morali</hi> by devine morall right. For albeit
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16324:13"/> (ſaith he) they be not ſo due, yet are they due by the free and now irrevocable conſecration of thoſe who were once Lords of them; In a fourth place, take <hi>Peter Marti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> iudgment, which is that notwithſtanding it was in the power of the ſupreme <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue and breake vp the ſocieties of Abbies and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, yet ſhould he then haue converted their houſes and revenewes to ſome other holy and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vſes, A thinge indeed, which <hi>Hen:</hi> the 8. ſolemne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promiſed to doe, vpon which condition that vaſt graunt of all religious houſes was made him, yea, a <note place="margin">Foxe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> thing which other places that emdraced reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as well as we, carefully did performe, for ſo I reade of the ſtate of <hi>Wittenbergh,</hi> in one <hi>Christopherus Bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derus</hi> quoted by M. <hi>Selden,</hi> in his Reviewe of the 9. and 10. Chapters of his hiſtory, as alſo of other parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> if wee may beleeue M. <hi>Brightman,</hi> either on the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> or the 11<hi rend="sup">h</hi>; In a fift roome let judicious <hi>Calvin</hi> bee, who is in the ſame note, when on the firſt of <hi>Hoſe,</hi> and 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> verſe, he ſtiles <hi>Hen:</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">h</hi> 
               <hi>Homo belluinus,</hi> a beaſtly man, becauſe as <hi>Iehu</hi> hee converted to his owne priuate prophane vſe, thoſe things which formerly had bin conſecrated to holy ones. In the 7. take in the opinion of thoſe Divines who wrott thoſe <hi>Scolia</hi> and compendious notes wee haue in our Engliſh Bibles, which they fully declare on ſeverall texts, but chiefly in that one the 6. of <hi>Ioſuah</hi> and the 19. as alſo that of <hi>Proverbs</hi> the 20. and the 25. To thoſe I might adde great <hi>Abulenſis</hi> in ſeverall places of his workes, together with ſeverall others, who though no friends to the <hi>ius divinum</hi> of tithes,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16324:13"/> becauſe the Popes vaſſalls doe yet with one conſent dogmatize them for robbers who in any degree pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane holy things. But I forbeare, fearing the time will outrunne my tongue; yet foraſmuch as I haue in my Catalogue of authority mentioned but one of the Laity, to witt M. <hi>Selden,</hi> wherevpon you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure imagine there is no more of that feather and ſo no ſummer of advantage thence to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, let me ſuccenturiate and add another, yea and he too a man of the ſword, by name S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> who hath written fullie to the ſame purpoſe in that his moſt learned, acute and zealous tract entituled <hi>de non temerandis eccleſiis,</hi> an Enchiridion written of purpoſe to perſwade an Vncle of his to the abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of an <hi>Appropriation;</hi> And thus as brieſly as I could, haue I made good both the propoſitions I laid downe. Now in the next place let me cleare ſuch <hi>quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> as are propoſed for the better vailing and pullia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Laities detayning of conſecrated goods. The one is made by the Lay Appropriator, and that thus, ſeeing I haue nothing but what at firſt I bought and now hold vnder the protection of an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, tell me, may I not with a quiet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe what is ſo backt and warranted, To whome I readily anſwere, No, For wouldeſt thou thinke thy ſelfe free from adultery, though an Act of Parliament ſhould allow thee foure or fiue wiues at once, or from the breach of the Lords day, though it ſhould licence thee to worke or ſport thy ſelfe, as much on that as on any other of the weeke, or from theft, though it ſhould conniue at thy pilfering, as ſome ſtates of old
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16324:14"/> haue done, If not then how can a ſtate iuſtly counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thee in thy doing that, by which thou commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſpirituall adultery, cauſeſt the day of ſanctified reſt to bee prophaned, and thoſe who through the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, might become Gods faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſtill through ignorance to remaine Sathans ſlaues; O, let no man hood-winke himſelfe with a conceit of the infallibility of a ſtate mett in a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as if their decrees were <hi>Sybillae folia</hi> meere ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, eſpecially when feare and covetuouſneſſe are the ſpeakers, as they vſually were in <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments: For if generall councells haue erred, and may againe in matters of faith, doubtleſſe the ſtate repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatiue hath, and may againe in matters of fact, And to put this out of all doubt, let me giue you a liſt of what fowle errors I haue obſerued to haue bin committed by the publique meetings of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and that ſince the daies of <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> wherein Religion hath moſt flouriſhed.</p>
            <p>Firſt I finde that <hi>William Rufus</hi> was admitted to the Imperiall Crowne of this Land, though <hi>Robert</hi> his elder Brother was living, and claymed his right.</p>
            <p>Secondly I finde, that <hi>Rufus</hi> being dead, the ſepter was put into the hand of <hi>Henry</hi> the youngeſt Sonne of the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> though <hi>Robert</hi> the eldeſt was not yet departed this life, thereby adding one wrong to another, a new to an old;</p>
            <p>Thirdly I finde that when <hi>Henry</hi> deceaſed, the ſtate receiued <hi>Stephen,</hi> and put by the Sonne of <hi>Henry</hi> the right heire.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it appeares there was a joynt conſent of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16324:14"/> both houſes for the depoſing of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, their true Soveraigne, and for the chooſing into his roome <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly wee reade how <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> was Crowned ſupreame of this Land, with the free conſent and applauſe of both houſes, though he were a Murtherer of his Nepheues, and ſo a plaine vſurper, yea the Parliament did entaile the Crowne on the ſonne of that Murtherer, though the two Daughters of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth were living.</p>
            <p>Sixtly it is manifeſt, that <hi>Henry</hi> the eights divorce from Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> was allowed and ratified by Parliament as being an inceſtuous marriage; and yet afterwards wee ſee the daughter of that Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi> preferred to the royall throne before bleſſed <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the daughter of his lawfull wife.</p>
            <p>Laſtly as a Parliament vnder <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Popery, ſo a Parliament within 6 yeares after, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> brought it in againe with triumph. To which I might annex many the like, if theſe were not abundantly ſufficient to make good my aſſertion, that Parliamentary decrees are many times lame and defectiue.</p>
            <p>O let then no lay perſon hereafter fly to that vaine fig-leafe excuſe, the ſtatute of the 31. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Abby lands and all tithes belonging vnto them <note place="margin">Chap. 13.</note> where conferrd on the King, when for certeine, there was never yet any learned Divine, whether <hi>Papiſt, Protestant</hi> or <hi>Nonconformitant,</hi> who <hi>de industria</hi> held it in the power of a ſtate to alienate and convert that to a temporall vſe, which was before devoted
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16324:15"/> and made over to a religious! Nay more I never yet heard of a iuditious layman who vpon mature conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the point, thought otherwiſe, Sure I am, Sir <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> who wrote the Common wealth of England, ſayes, a Parliament hath onlie power to change the right and poſſeſſion of private men; Vpon the hearing of which, if any Appropriator ſhall ſay vnto mee, togeather with other Paſtors, as thoſe Iewes did to S. <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſttles, when reprooued for their ſinnes, men and bretheren what ſhall I and others who are in the ſame caſe doe? <note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> how ſhall wee eſcape the curſe you ſay attends on vs? Would you haue vs render vp our tithes, and ſo ſet our gates wide open to beggery? Surely not as yet vntill all other meanes of redreſſe faile, I ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you to another courſe which is farre eaſier, It is, that you and others who hold tithes would imitate thoſe <hi>Philiſtins</hi> of <hi>Aſhdod</hi> after they became ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their vniuſt deteining the Arke of the God of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> for as they ſaid to the Princes of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> what ſhall wee doe with the Arke of God? the firſt of <hi>Samuell</hi> the 5. So would I haue you to repaire to the Princes of this Land, when ever met together about the Kingdomes waightie affaires, and ſay vnto them, what ſhall wee doe with the maintenance of Gods Arke the Church? As by an Act of this great Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly wee poſſeſſe tithes, ſo let vs bee quit of them by an act of yours alſo, and yet let your wiſedomes ſo provide for Gods glorie, as not vtterly to impoveriſh our families;</p>
            <p>I but what if the eares of both houſes bee ſhut vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16324:15"/> our iterated importunate petitions, what ſhall wee then doe? Truly, rather then to keepe Gods curſe ſtill with you. I would adviſe you to doe by your grants and patents, as <hi>Iudas</hi> did by the thirtie peices of ſilver hee received of the chiefe Prieſts and elders for betraying of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> even to caſt them downe in theſe Churches and Oratories from whence they were firſt taken; Nor want I a patterne for this my counſell. In the ſecond of <hi>Cronicles</hi> and the 25. you may read, that when <hi>Amaziah</hi> king of <hi>Iudah</hi> had hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a hundred thouſand men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to increaſe his Armie, there came a man of God vnto him ſaying, <hi>O King let not the Armie of Iſrael goe with thee, for the Lord is not with Iſrael, as having beene vniuſtly rent from the houſe of Dauid,</hi> So ſay I from the Lord, vnto all that haue purchaſed tithes for the increaſe of their eſtates, O Brethren let not theſe tithes abide with you, for the Lord is not with them, becauſe miſplac'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe rent from the true Proprietaries the Lords Prieſts, and when the king ſaid vnto the <hi>Prorhet</hi> vpon the hearing of this meſſage, what ſhall I doe for the hundred talents I haue giuen to the Army of <hi>Iſraell?</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> replyed, the Lord is able to giue thee much more then this. So if any Impropriator ſhall ſay vnto mee in his owne and his felowes behalfe, But what I pray ſhall wee doe for the money wee haue payd for our patents? My Anſwere muſt bee as the <hi>Prophets</hi> was Let not the loſſe of your money bee a <hi>remora</hi> a hold-back vnto you For the Lord is able to giue you much more then thoſe ſummes. And thus much in anſwer vnto the firſt <hi>Quaere</hi> made in defence
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16324:16"/> of thoſe laymen who poſſeſſe ſacred tithes ſuch as were at firſt conſecrated to Gods glory in the reward of the Churches Paſtors.</p>
            <p>A ſecond now followes, &amp; it is fram'd by thoſe who are fellonious vniuſt detainers of tithes by cuſtomes; What (ſay they) doe you ſtampe the letter R. on our fore-heads aſwell as on the Impropriators? Doe you make vs theeues and robbers too? Yes verily, you likewiſe fall within the verge of the ſame cenſure, As for your allegation, that you pay ſomethinge in lieu of your tithes, two pence peradventure for two ſhilling, it is no better an excuſe then his might bee, who having ſtolne a Gooſe, ſhould ſay, I brought backe the wings and feathers, or his, who after hee hath conveyed away the body of a fatt Wether, ſhould plead, O but I left the skinne behind for the right owner; Nay it would be a worſe excuſe then that of <hi>Dioniſius</hi> of <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> when he tooke from the ſtatue of <hi>Iupiter Olympus</hi> a Cloake of gold, and left one of Cloath, ſaying that of gold was too heauy for ſommer, and cold for winter; it is an <hi>axiome, Gradus non variant ſpecies,</hi> though one theft be greater then another, yet the leaſt is ſtill theft. I muſt confeſſe if two things were once well proved, neither of which is poſſible to be done, no not by the helpe of thoſe cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Tutors of Sacriledge, the Divells of Hell, then Cuſtom-pleaders and Enioyers, might goe free from the guilt of Church-robbery, the one, that tithes are not due to the <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> of the Goſpell <hi>iure diuino morali,</hi> the other that Patrons who at firſt endowed the Churches with tithes, appointed leſſe to be payed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16324:16"/> then the tenth of all increaſe; As for the laſt, if you conſult our ſuppoſed adverſary, M. <hi>Selden</hi> in the 8. Chapter of his Hiſtory, you ſhall finde there a <hi>conge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and heape of Donations and Graunts of all tithes in kinde in this kingdome, as alſo edicts of ſtate for due performance, according to thoſe conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Graunts; And yet leaſt you might imagine I goe too much alone in this path, let me here acquaint you with what the whole current of <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> ſay concerning this poynt of cuſtomes; In brieſe when the queſtion is made whether cuſtome may iuſtly carry with it the force and ſtrength of a law; I find they diſtinguiſh of Cuſtomes, and tell the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders there is one which is vicious and naught, as bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to reaſon, which though vnconſionable men will pleade, yet doth it not excuſe, much leſſe obteyne the force of a law which is according to that no leſſe true then common ſaying, <hi>multitudo er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantium nonfacit patrocinium,</hi> the multitude of thoſe who erre is no patronage of the error <hi>niſi conſuetudo ratione munita ſit, non eſt conſuetudo, ſed corruptela</hi> vnleſſe Cuſtome bee backt by reaſon it is not cuſtome, but a crept in abuſe or corruption; Agreeable to which, is likewiſe that of S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> they doe in vaine cry <hi>Custome Custome</hi> who are ouercome &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uinced by reaſon, otherwiſe ſaith hee Cuſtome would bee greater then truth. Another Cuſtome there is (ſay they) which is laudable and no way repugnant to the rectitude of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and ſuch an on they allow to bee of as much force and vertue as a law, if not repeald by the ſupreme Magiſtrate, yea to differ from a law
<pb facs="tcp:16324:17"/> only <hi>in modo</hi> in the manner of its being A law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliuered by writing, but Cuſtome only by vſe, And in this ſenſe is that of <hi>Iulianus</hi> the <hi>Civlian</hi> to bee taken, <hi>inueterata conſuetudo pro lege non immerito cuſtoditur,</hi> Now to apply this diſtinction to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in hand, tell mee, can any one of you who heares mee this day, ſay, without giuing the lye to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that a Cuſtome of paying a peny for a ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling falls vnder the head of a good and laudable on? you heard even now, that cuſtome is only good, which is reaſonable; Anſwere mee then, doth it ſtand with reaſon, any man ſhould enforce his brother, nay more his father) for ſo each Paſtor is to his flocck) to take either nothing, or but a peny in lieu of that which is well worth a ſhilling? Is this (I pray) a reaſonable &amp; an honeſt ſatisfaction? Nor can any man without put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the vizard of impudencie, produce here the Statute either of the 27. or the 32. of <hi>Hcn.</hi> the 8. or the 2. of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. For albeit thoſe at the firſt bluſh may ſeeme to ratify and make good all cuſtomes in payment of tithes, yet for certeyne they ſay no more then what I haue already told you from an vnanimous conſent of Claſſique Authors. Namely that no other Cuſtomes are to bee allowed in diſcharge of tithes, then what are laudable and lawfull, which Epithites you ſhalbee fure to meete withall, in thoſe Statutes, whereby it euidently appeares, they approue not of all thoſe Cuſtomes, which in caſe of tithes the deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate corruption of this <hi>Mammon-ſeruing age,</hi> calles and cryes for,</p>
            <p>Bleſſed then is the Councell of <hi>Iſiodor</hi> (hee was a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16324:17"/> father of the Church in his time) <hi>conſuetudo authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati cedat, prauum vſum lex et ratio vincat.</hi> Let cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome (ſaith hee) giue place to authority, and let law and reaſon conquer a bad vſe, where by law hee meanes (ſaith <hi>Aquinas)</hi> that of nature, that which preacheth to euery ſonne of <hi>Adam, doe as thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bee done by;</hi> That which in ſubſtance is all on with the Decalogue, that laſtly the tranſgreſſion whereof God complaynes of in the verſe before the text, and that with a kind of admiration. Will a man rob his God? this being a fact almoſt incredible becauſe it ſlatly goes againſt the very light of nature. And ſo much in anſwere to the Second <hi>Quaere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third apologizing on is this; What is it not a ſufficient reaſon for a ſtate to alienate tithes and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings becauſe conſecrated vnder ſuperſtition and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry?</p>
            <p>Surely no, nor will the Appropriator, (I knowe) vpon due balanceing of the buſineſſe bee of another opinion; For if the donations of tithes, may <hi>de iure</hi> of right bee diſannulled by a State, becauſe made vnder Superſtition, then why may not the ſame power by the ſame right now make void all their grants and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of Tithes and other Church reuenewes, becauſe conueyed vnto them when ſuperſtition no leſſe ruled &amp; raigned, yea to lay ſuch a foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for <hi>Hen:</hi> the 8. his confiſcation of Tithes, glebes and the like ſacred Incomes, were to bring into queſtion at this day the right of moſt mens poſſeſſions, and ſo by conſequent turne the Common wealth into a wofull Chaos of confuſion: And yet leaſt this pretext againſt Tithes
<pb facs="tcp:16324:18"/> ſhould for all this, receiue a glad welcome amongeſt many, let mee further giue you to vnderſtand, that to ſuppoſe tithes as conſecrated vnder Romiſh ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this Kingdome, is to build an <hi>Eutopia,</hi> to lay a foundation <hi>in ipſo vacuo;</hi> For tithes were generally dedicated to the worſhip of God when firſt the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious vncorrupted light of the Goſpell did ſhine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, before ever true popery was <hi>in rerum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura,</hi> before thoſe times came, which loſt the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue faith of Rome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr</hi> 
               <hi>Selden</hi> may ſerue as a ſpectacle to help the dimme ignorance of moſt men in this point, Nor is yet the Impropriator quiet, hee hath on obiection more, by which hee hopes to ſet the broad ſeale of the worlds wide applauſe, to that of their patents from <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8. It is thus propoſed.</p>
            <p>But may not thoſe things bee iuſtly confiſcated which were giuen as ſupporting pillers to ſuperſtition, might not thoſe tithes bee <hi>ad placitum Senatus</hi> at the diſpoſition of a Parliament, which were found to haue been imployed to ſuperſtition, euen to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of <hi>Maſſes</hi> for the quick and dead?</p>
            <p>I ſay confidently No, And that for two reaſons chiefely; The one is drawne from that precept which God gaue concerning the Cenſers of thoſe 250. Rebells in the 16. of <hi>Numbers,</hi> which was, they ſhould bee beaten into Plates for the Alter, though they had lately been abuſd to his diſhonor. If then the all-wiſe God thought it fit that thoſe Cenſers ſhould bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to a holy vſe which now had been deuoted to rebellion, ſhall our ignorance bee ſo proud as to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16324:18"/> inuent a newe plat forme of diſpoſing abuſed tithes? ſhall wee deeme it fit to alienate them for ever from all holy and pious vſes? Doubtleſſe a ſtander by, on not engaged in the quarrell will call this by no better name then a miſhapen brat, framed partly of coue. touſneſſe, and partly fond ſelfe conceite;</p>
            <p>The other lyes in that reaſon which tranſcendent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iudicious <hi>Auſtine</hi> gaue in this very point, It is in his 15. <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Publicula,</hi> where ſpeaking of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Idolls, and their Groues and Temples, iudged they were not to bee conuerted to priuate vſes, but to publique, and that (ſaith hee) leaſt it ſhould ſeeme to haue been done rather by auarice then deuotion; Nor doth that <hi>Imperiall</hi> decree any way make good a Kingdomes tranſpoſing of holy places and Reuenues, The words of it bee theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnia loca &amp;c.</hi> Wee command that all places <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Paga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; ſacrifi tit.</hi> 14.</note> which the error of the Antients aſſigned to Sacrifices to bee appropriated to our eſtate, which aſſertion of mine wil eaſily be receiued for a truth by al thoſe who will be pleaſed to conſider what places the Emperors willed to bee appropriated, Namly ſuch only as were aſſigned to the Idolatrous ſacrifices of <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Pagans.</hi> Now who is there ſo bat-ſighted, as not to diſcerne what difference there is betweene houſes and lands dedicated to <hi>Pagan</hi> ſuperſtition, and tithes which were at firſt deuoted as a ſalary of the ſpirituall Paſtors paines, and afterwards only through the boundleſſe authority of the <hi>Pope</hi> to ſuperſtition. And what more euident demonſtration can there bee, that thoſe very Emperors <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> put a
<pb facs="tcp:16324:19"/> great Chaſme of difference betweene things dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto paganiſme, &amp; thoſe which had beene amiſſe conſecrated vnro <hi>Chriſtianiſme,</hi> then that they are ſo farre from confiſcating both kinds, as to decree the conuerting of the on to holy vſes though not the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>In the Code of <hi>Theodotius</hi> it is thus enacted. Let <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 16. <hi>tit.</hi> 44. <hi>Contra Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtas.</hi>
               </note> thoſe poſſeſſions where direfull ſuperſtition hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto raigned bee annexed to the venerable Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, and in the ſame place wee find a Decree of thoſe Emperors againſt the <hi>Montaniſts</hi> in theſe words If there bee any of their edifices ſtanding which are rather to bee termed the dennes of wild beaſts then Churches let them with their reuenues bee appropriated to the ſacred Churches of the <hi>orthodox</hi> faith: And for ampler proofe that godly <hi>Emperors</hi> when they expelld the hereticall party did not ſpoile their Churches of theire poſſeſſions, but reſtored them to the true Profeſſors, I call S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his 50. <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Bonifacius</hi> a Souldiour; his words bee theſe; <hi>Quicquid ergo nomine eccleſiarum partis donati poſſide batur, Chriſtiani Imperatores legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus religioſis cum ipſis Fccleſiis, ad Catholicam tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re iuſserunt.</hi> And who needs ſpectacles to ſee how it was only filthy auarice which made this ſtate to doe otherwiſe at that great day of diſſolution of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous houſes? For if it had been ſanctified zeale, why did they not at the ſame time pull downe an diſpoſe of the very ſtones and timber of their Churches, whenas they had been as fully dedicated and more abuſed to ſuperſtition then ever the tithes which belonged vnto
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16324:19"/> them? But <hi>in promtu ratio,</hi> the reaſon is playne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then their purſes muſt haue prouided new ones without a diſpenſation from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> freely to vſe their Barnes or other roomes in their priuat hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes inſtead of temples, To ſumme vp then my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to this <hi>quaere,</hi> Wee ought not ſo much to loocke to the prophanition of tithes as to their firſt donation, which was to a pious end, euen to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the ſacred <hi>miniſtery</hi> of the Church. So that when the ſuperſtitious &amp; idolatrous vſe was aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they ought to haue been returnd to their primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and lawfull vſe. A leading paterne to which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete Act, wee haue in the practice of the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt towards the Arke, which though it had beene taken and abuſed by the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> did not, after it was ſent home, imagine the former conſecration to bee expired and loſt, but honored and reuerenced it as much as euer they did before;</p>
            <p>And ſecondly towards the veſſells and ornaments of the Temple, which though they had bin carried by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to <hi>Babilon</hi> and there abuſed by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put into the Temple of his Gods, yet were they afterwards admitted to the ſame holy vſe as they were before in the ſeruice of their true God;</p>
            <p>Nor as yet haue I done with this Accuſation of God, the pronoune <hi>(me) yee haue robbed mee,</hi> offers on note more worthy your attentiue obſeruation, and thats this,</p>
            <p>God reckons of all as of theeues and Robbers of himſelfe, who any way rob and ſpoile his Prieſts, the word Prieſt I rather vſe then any other, both becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:16324:20"/> it is a name which properly belongs to none but thoſe who ſerue at Gods Alter, when as that of <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> without ſome additio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to vs with Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Tinkers, or men of any other inferiour office, As alſo, becauſe it is that name whoſe very ſound works as ſtrange an effect on the Sacrilegiſt his guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as that which ſtories tell vs the ſound of a drumme couered with a woulfes skinne doth on ſilly ſheepe, euen the diſtemper of feare and horror. The note cannot bee though leſſe then legitinate as long as the <hi>(mee)</hi> ſtands in the Text. Neither wants there preſſing and vrgent reaſon to beleeue that the Lord is ſo tender of the wronges which are done to vs the Paſtors of ſoules,</p>
            <p>Firſt wee are his Ambaſſadours, and therefore hee takes whatſoeuer poſitiue diſgraces, or but priuatiue neglects are ſhowne vnto vs, to reflect and redound directly on his ſacred Magieſtie.</p>
            <p>Secondly ſeeing tithes &amp; offerings are all the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hee hath allotted vs for the paines wee take in his vineyard, how can hee account it leſſe then an affront to him ſelfe, when we are robed of thoſe his penſions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly ſeing hee by the cleare perſpectiue of his omniſcient wiſedome lookes into mens hearts, and there finds the chiefe cauſe of their hard meaſure to vs to arriſe from our faithfull execution of his roiall Commiſſions, how can ſo iuſt a Iudge but take thoſe iniuries to heart?</p>
            <p>Many parralells to this zeale of Gods, wee meete withall in the Scriptures, witnes that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> why perſecuteſt thou mee? Acts the 9. where our Sauiour
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16324:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> accounts himſelfe as perſecuted, though in Heauen, when his <hi>Church</hi> is ſo on earth.</p>
            <p>Againe witneſſe that his bill of inditement againſt the wicked at the laſt day <hi>Mathew</hi> the 25. <hi>I was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and yee gaue mee not to eate, I was thirsty and yee gaue mee not to drinke,</hi> To which when the wicked ſhall tremblingly reply <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> when <hi>Lord</hi> did wee ſee thee ſo? hee ſhall plainly tell them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, In as much as yee haue not done it to my poore members, yee haue not done it vnto mee.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe laſtly that of <hi>Iudges</hi> the 5. <hi>Where the Angell of the Lord commands the Citty of Meroſh to bee curſed bitterly,</hi> and that becauſe they came not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iehovah,</hi> to the help of the Lord where the Lord takes their flinty hard heartedneſſe towards their brethren as ſhowne to himſelfe, Tell mee then, O thou who makeſt thy ſelfe an embleme of wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe by defrauding any Paſtor through Cuſtomes or otherwiſe, Are not thy thoughts troubled? Are not the ioynts of thy loynes looſened? And doe not thy knees ſmite on againſt another at the hearing of this.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Daniell</hi> ſets before vs <hi>Baltaſer</hi> in that wofull plight inflicted as a due reward of his propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the conſecrated veſſells of the temple, how then canſt thou bee free from an earthquake of feare and dread, who daily deuoureſt that which is holy, who daily conuerts that to thine owne vſe, which thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed forefathers frely deuoted to God in the perpetuall mayntenance of his ſeruice? And ſo I haſten to my laſt generall circumſtance, which is the vniuerſality of
<pb facs="tcp:16324:21"/> the ſinne, <hi>Gens tota,</hi> euen the whole Nation,</p>
            <p>That is ſaith <hi>Ribera,</hi> your Princes and rich men are Robbers, of mee aſwell as your poore &amp; priuate ons, yea it is as much as if he had ſaid in more words thus, It is true O yee men of <hi>Iudah</hi> the Lord blames you by me for many ſins, for adultery ſorcery, falſe ſwearing, &amp; diuers others yet not ſo, as if all theſe were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by you all, but for the ſin of ſacriledge he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demns you all, being generally the Act of you all; So <hi>Vata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blas,</hi> whence I may well inferre this concluſion.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible that a whole Nation may at once make a defection from God by ſome one tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that that ſin which heretofore hath bin but perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall or at moſt but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to fewe, may at length be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Nationall, Experience prompts vnto vs that the ſonne which now is ecclepſed but in part, may at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time be wholy, That a ſound member of the true Church of God may ere long become a ſynagogue of Sathan; May not Conſpiracy and treaſon at length poſſeſſe the breſts of thoſe who are now moſt faithfull and loyall ſubiects? May it not befall a Kingdome in reſpect of ſpirituall fruitfullneſſe, as it did <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> in reſpect of earthly? For as that tract of ground became from on of the worlds paradiſes, the Center as it were of deſolate barrenneſſe, ſo may not a Kingdome which now is another <hi>Alcinous</hi> garden full of herbs of grace, and fruits of pleaſure, become a wilderneſſe of nothing but ſtincking weeds, and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full briars and brambles? If the old world did wholly fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, may not one little territory of the new? And if the whole <hi>Christian vniuerſe</hi> did once lye
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16324:21"/> groueling vnder the curſed apoſtaſy of <hi>Arianiſme,</hi> &amp; thereby did ſeeme (as Reuerend Hooker ſpeakes) to haue giuen vp the very ghoſt of true beleefe, then why may not one part of it lye bedridden (as it were) with the Cramp of Sacriledge? Surely the defection of one Kingdome in point of fact, is farre more eaſy then a Chriſtian worlds in point of tenent and beleefe.</p>
            <p>But here ſome one may demand of mee was there none in the populous tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> who made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of following the very dictate of nature in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God tithes and offerings in his Prieſts? Did each wilfully put out that light of Knoledge the ſeeds whereof they brought into the world with them? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no, Charity teaches mee to enterpret this <hi>Gens tota</hi> the whole Nation by that diſtinction of the Scholes, made by reaſon of the word <hi>omnes</hi> all. This all (ſay they) is put ſometimes to ſignify <hi>ſingula generum.</hi> each of euery Kind: and ſometimes <hi>genera tantum ſingulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> only the ſeuerall Kinds and ſpecies, and ſo, though this <hi>gens tota</hi> make ſome of euery Kind and ſtate of <hi>Iudah</hi> guilty, yet doth it not each in euery kinde. Such phraſes are but hyperboles, involuing the moſt and not all; It is ſufficient the denomination is after the greater part, Hee that makes Italy the Nurſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of villaines, drunkenneſſe the badge of a Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and pride the ſhadowe of a Spaniard, ſayes not each in theſe places is ſo qualified, at the moſt, his words can bee ſcrewed no higher then that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part is ſo.</p>
            <p>Or yet if you will you may take this <hi>gens tota</hi> to bee meant as it ſounds, euen to includ each particular
<pb facs="tcp:16324:22"/> in <hi>Iudah,</hi> and to inferre that the leauen of Sacriledge was found vnder euery ones roofe, and that thus, The moſt of them might bee delinquents in Act, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder in deſire and wiſh, the moſt by the theft of the hand and heart, the reſt by the theft of the heart only. you well know all the Commandements are as well broken by ſecret wiſhes and purpoſes, as by viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and open Acts, feare of incurring ſome temporall puniſhment might hold back ſome from doing of that which conſcience could not; yea the hope of ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage which might arriſe, might make thoſe iuſt in payment of their tithes, who otherwiſe would haue had as deep a hand in robbery as the worſt, God the maker, and therfore ſearcher of the heart condemnes or iuſtifies by the workes of the heart, <hi>Abiſhai</hi> is ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his brother in killing of <hi>Abner</hi> though wee find <hi>Ioab</hi> only ſtroke him, and that becauſe his heart ſtroke him aſwell as <hi>Ioabs</hi> hand; <hi>Cain</hi> (ſaith <hi>Philo Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus)</hi> was not only curſed afrer hee had murdered his brother but before, euen as ſoone as euer hee had hatched ſuch a thought he giues the reaſon <hi>voluntate profacto aeſtimata</hi> his will and purpoſe being taken for the deede,</p>
            <p>It was a groſſe error of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> the Iewe, when hee reprehended <hi>Polibius</hi> the heathen, for ſaying <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> died miſerably becauſe hee had reſolu'd with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to haue ſpoiled the temple of <hi>Diana;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Excellent to this purpoſe is that of <hi>Austine, nemo inuitus benefacit, etiamſi bonum eſt quod facit.</hi> No man who is vnwilling doth good though the thing bee good which hee doth; To which let mee add that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16324:22"/> of <hi>Seneca</hi> to <hi>Serenus, Poteſt aliquis nocens fieri, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis non nocuerit,</hi> A man may bee a nocent when hee hurts not; hee proues it by inſtances, A man ſaith hee though hee lyes with his owne wife co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mits adultery, if hee take her to bee another, and hee is guilty of murther who runnes a ſword againſt his breſt, who by chance hath a coate of Male on, ſo doubtles may they bee well ſtiled Robbers, who in heart contriue and plot how to embeazell thoſe tithes and offerings which yet peraduenture they ſtill miſſe of compaſſing And thus haue I <hi>Ionas-like</hi> paſſed through the ſtreets and quarters of the text, and yet haue I not finiſhed my intended taske; I ſhould now parralell this our <hi>Iudah</hi> of <hi>England</hi> with that of the Iewes, and ſhew you that as wee haue been made like to them in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying ſhowers of fauours beyond other Nations, ſo haue wee already with them, and ſhall hereafter farre more bee curſed, if wee like them continue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> greedy deuourers &amp; cunning Subſtractors of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all goods; Say I but like them, yea farr more then euer they, and that in that <hi>gens tota</hi> diminiſheth our tithes by vnlawfull (becauſe vnconſcionable) cuſtomes, a thing neuer dreamd of amongſt the Iewes, much leſſe made good by ſeting falſe and counterfeit gloſſes on the lawes iuſt intents, But I perceiue your patience is ſo farre ſpent, that the worke of my tongue muſt proue a lame Giles by falling ſhort of the intention of my heart, only let mee add one word of exhortation, and ſo an end.</p>
            <p>I beſeech all you beloued who haue heard mee this day, and that in the name of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> that you
<pb facs="tcp:16324:23"/> deale not by what you haue heard as you vſe to do by your old apparrell when worne to ragges, that is not to lay it aſide with a purpoſe neuer more to think of it, but meditate and ponder on it with reſolution of preferring heauens euerlaſting ioyes before this worlds vaniſhing trifles, And thou O Omnipotent Lord who gaueſt ſuch power and efficacy to one Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peters,</hi> as thereby to add about three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſoules to the viſible number of the faithfull, add (I moſt humbly beſeech thee) by my this dayes miniſtery, at leaſt one ſoule to thy inuiſible flock, and that for thy ſonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> his ſake &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:16324:23"/>
            <head>A POST-SCRIPT</head>
            <p>READER I iudge it requiſite to acquaint you with two things thereby to prevent the iniury thou may'st o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe doe thy ſelfe and mee, The on is That I am farre from doubting of the <hi>ius diuinum</hi> of Tithes, though I ſay little of it in this Sermon; yea ſo farr, as my beleife of it is but one degree ſhort of his, who made the Tenent of the Popes being Anti-Chriſt part of his Creed, I haue of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe forborne that Tract, becauſe I finde it already made ſmooth and plaine by the happy induſtrie of many a <note n="*" place="margin">The late R. B. of Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegue Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells Perrot S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Iames Simple &amp; others.</note> learned pen, when as this other on which I ſhall ſet footing, is toucht by few, and thoſe too <hi>obiter</hi> rather then <hi>de induſtria.</hi> The other particuler of which I am to informe thee is, That I quarrell not Biſhops and Prebendaries enioying of Tithes, ſo that two things may paſſe for currant truth, the one that thoſe Biſhops and Prebendaries are to bee thought to haue the cheife charge of thoſe mens ſoules from whome they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Tithes, and not the Vicars who indeed are but their Curats. The other that it were fitt they were interdicted from letting, and ſetting their Tithes (especially to Laicks) for longer ſpace then their owne liues And thus friendly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thou haſt my inſide turned outward in the poynt of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated dewes. The cenſure of which I only ſubmit to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sanedrim the houſe of Conuocation as taking that body to bee the only competent and fit deciſiue iudge in buſineſſe of this nature. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. E. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="questions">
            <pb facs="tcp:16324:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16324:24"/>
            <head>A CATALOGVE OF SVCH QVAERES <hi>as are ſubmitted by the Author in all due reſpect to the Iudgment of the wiſeſt ſonnes of his mother the Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1 VVHether Sacriledge may not bee called the worſhipping of Mammon?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether the Sacriledgïſt his loue to tithes bee not worſe Idolatrie, then a Papiſt his praying ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Sainct or Angell?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether our forefathers, who liued before <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8. dayes, might not haue been more aſſured of their ſaluation, though dying Papiſts, then any Puritan Church-robber now can bee if ſo dying?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether thoſe who labour for a penſionary Clergy are not therein ſecret vnderminers of <hi>Caeſars</hi> throne? Or thus, whether the touching of Gods Prieſts by inforced beggery, lead not directly to the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the King by a minoration of his iuſt Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether the ſcapes and errors of whatſoeuer faulty ones there bee in the Clergy, may not in part bee iuſtly laied to the charge of Church-robbers, and not only to the tinder-like corruption of <hi>humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or the ſudaine blaſts of Satans cunning tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether a Patron hath the leaſt couler of
<pb facs="tcp:16324:25"/> reaſon to expect that his Clerke ſhould conſionably performe the office of a Paſtor after he hath enforced him to add periury to Simony, and that in a breath?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether it ſtands not with the rule of equall proportion, the Patron ſhould take an oath hee nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath or will take any thing, directly or indirectly for his Praeſentation, as well as the Clerke, hee neither hath or will giue any thing? Herein only the ſupreme Maieſty being excepted, becauſe ſuch a tranſcendent as cannot (being once crowned,) bee put to an oath, without great derogation?</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether hee may not bee accompted hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critically partiall who hauing ſeuerall towne ſhips and mannors, holds it lawfull to diſcharge his duty in thoſe places by his Bailiffs and Rent gatherers, &amp; yet will by noe meanes allow that Diuine to teach a Flock, by the ſubſtitution of an able Curate whom the pinching tyranny of Sacriledge hath enforced to accept of a ſecond Benifice.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether it bee not apparent by that of the ſecond to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> the 11. and the 8. That S. <hi>Paule</hi> tooke Maintenance from on place whilſt hee was reſident in another?</p>
            <p n="10">10. Whether it may not truly bee ſaid the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puritan makes vp a religion of his owne, whilſt hee is not content to allow his teacher more then the poore pittance of Fifty pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> though cloggd with a long heauy chaine of domeſtick expences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſids the want of bookes, when as not only all ſound <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papists,</hi> but likewiſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cartwright,</hi> with all the iuditious of that ſtamp doe clayme a libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:16324:25"/> &amp; plentiful entertainment, ſuch a one as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may bee able to anſwere the Apoſtles Iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> louers of Hoſpitality?</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whether in probability the Knoledge of <hi>Chriſt</hi> which is the foundation may not ſooner bee loſt through their meanes, who runne the next way to the banniſhing of all ſolid learning, then by them who labour by learning to vphold their errors.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Whats the reaſon why they who are moſt ſacrilegious in withholding tithes from the Prieſt, doe moſt cry-out againſt vniuerſality of grace, and mans freedome to goodneſſe?</p>
            <p n="13">13. May it not bee imagined, they intend here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there prophanation of holy thinges to the charge of God, becauſe hee giues them not wills to a bandon ſo ſweet a Darling <hi>Ganymeded</hi> ſinne.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16324:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
